Alright בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So today's דף daf is טז tet
zayin and we pick up at the top of טז עמוד א
tet zayin amud aleph and we have just read the משנה Mishnah
of the second פרק perek and the משנה Mishnah told us
that a case where they're debating not why wasn't she a virgin
on the wedding night, you know, but thank you, but why was
it 20 years later she's getting divorced and there's no כתובה ketubah
and whether actually it was a first wedding or second wedding? And
that's what they're debating what happens during the wedding, yeah, not what
her physical state was the wedding night, but had it been a
first wedding or second wedding? And there the גמרא Gemara says that
in that case you need witnesses to testify to the sort of
indicators that it was a first wedding. Talks about how she left
her father's home and with the whole big major production or whether
they
had the roasted grain or other types of things that would be
an indicator for whether it was a first wedding or second wedding,
whether 300 people invited to the ceremony etc. Anyway, so without those
indicators though she would not be believed because basically the principle of
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. But the גמרא Gemara
now wants to understand how does that fit in with the debate
of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? Let's take
a look.
טעמא Ta'ama says the גמרא, Gemara, we learn on the top of
טז עמוד א, tet zayin amud aleph, the reason that she would
win this case is דאיכא עדים, de'ika edim, only if there are
witnesses that show that it was a first wedding. הליכא עדים, Haleka
edim, without the presence of witnesses במהימנא bam'aimana the husband would be
believed.
לימא דלא כרבן גמליאל, Leima d'lo k'Rabban Gamliel, let's say that's not
going like Rabban Gamliel, because you remember Rabban Gamliel normally says she's
believed, which is really asking us to remember why does Rabban Gamliel
say that she's believed, right? Why don't we apply the normal principle
of המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה? Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah? So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara tells us. So the גמרא Gemara says דברי
רבן גמליאל היא מהימנא, divrei Rabban Gamliel hi m'aimana, he says she's
believed. So the גמרא Gemara says אפילו תימא רבן גמליאל, afillu teima
Rabban Gamliel, could even be Rabban Gamliel. עד כאן לא קאמר רבן
גמליאל התם אלא בברי ושמא.
ad kan lo ka'amar Rabban Gamliel hatam ella
b'bari v'shema. One of the reasons that Rabban Gamliel believed her, the
most significant reason, although the גמרא Gemara says it doesn't mean he'd
say every ברי ושמא, bari v'shema, the גמרא Gemara gave us as
we'll see in a minute some things that also strengthen her case,
but it started with the fact that she's making a definite claim,
she knows why her physical state was that of not being a
virgin and he doesn't. So her ברי bari was believed over his
שמא. shema. אבל הכא ברי וברי לא,
Aval hacha bari
v'bari lo, but here each one is saying that they know absolutely,
she's saying I know it was a first wedding, he says what
are you talking about, that was a second wedding, you'd been married
before. So each one is making a definite claim. We don't know
who's telling the truth but each one is making a definite claim.
Okay wait let's get a little further. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אבל
ברי ושמא לא, אבל הכא ברי וברי לא אמר.
aval bari v'shema lo, aval hacha bari v'bari
lo amar. ודקארי ליה מאי קארי ליה? V'dakari lei mai kari lei?
So here's a question we would like to ask a lot of
times. So what was the what were you thinking in the first
place? Obviously there's that difference, right? Obviously here they're both making a
definite claim and in the previous case it was a ברי bari
and a שמא. shema. Clearly that's a difference. The גמרא Gemara says
מאי קארי ליה, mai kari lei, so הכא ברי וברי הוא, hacha
bari v'bari hu, this is clearly each one making a definite claim
and it's your classic המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah.
So the
גמרא Gemara
says הכא ברי וברי הוא, לא. hacha bari v'bari hu, lo. כיון
דרוב נשים בתולות נישאות, Kivun d'rov nashim betula nis'ot, since most of
the weddings are first weddings, ברוך השם, baruch Hashem, I mean you
know hasn't gotten that bad that most of the time, you know,
although they use this statistic, right? Like they say 50% of marriages
end in divorce but
that doesn't mean for a second
marriage.
But besides that, I think that statistic is misleading. I think what
it means is is that like 50% of the weddings that take
place are second like might be second marriages or something but like
it could often like or not what it means is like this,
like some people are get divorced a lot of times. So therefore
50% of the marriages end in divorce don't mean 50% of the
people who get married, of the unique people who get married get
divorced. Anyway, but okay ברוך השם baruch Hashem we've got a case
of what do you call that most of the time it's a
first it's a first marriage. So כיון דרוב נשים בתולות נישאות, kivun
d'rov nashim betula nis'ot, most women get married it's a first marriage,
so I mean literally virgin but here the emphasis being first marriage.
So כי ברי ושמא דמי, ki bari v'shema dami, the claim that
no it was a second marriage is a weaker claim, it's not
a ברי bari in terms of the טענה ta'ana that's a ברי
טענה bari ta'ana but in terms of its believability he's on slightly
weaker footing than she is. So I might have thought that, right?
And I might have thought therefore that Rabban Gamliel would would still
believe her in this case even though they're both ברי. bari. אוקיי
והכי נמי מסתברא. Okay v'hacha nami mistavra. Oh yeah, then this makes
sense.
So why
don't because it's המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. It's
to I mean the גמרא Gemara is going to get to it
later. You know, if you say would you go by a רוב
rov to be מוציא ממון, motzi mammon, the normal principle is אין
הולכין בממון אחר הרוב. ein holchin b'mammon achar harov. Just because it's
like 70% likely she's telling the truth, that's not going to be
enough. I mean she's making a definite claim and he's saying definitely
not. So you need some real evidence in that case. Okay, so
let's say but the גמרא Gemara will deal with it a little
bit later. It all this ties into the question of הולכין בממון
אחר הרוב. holchin b'mammon achar harov. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, והכי נמי
מסתברא, v'hacha nami mistavra, that makes sense that Rabban Gamliel is basically
conceding this point and he's okay. and he's conceding this point because
it's ברי וברי, bari u'bari, even though you might have wanted to
call it a type of a ברי ושמא. bari v'shema. He's saying,
"This case, I will concede that even that even though you might
want to argue, I would argue this case and call it a
ברי ושמא. bari v'shema. No, this case is a ברי וברי. bari
u'bari. This case, this case I'm going to concede that she's not
going to win." So הכי נמי מסתברא hachi nami mistavra that רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is like conceding this case. ומדתני, u'midtani, the end
of the משנה Mishnah says ומודה רבי יהושע u'modeh Rabi Yehoshua that
רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua concedes in a case where a guy says,
"This field was your father's and I bought it from him," right?
רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua normally says that we don't, you know, that
we don't believe the guy's טענה, tayna, and here it says that
we will because here it's, you know, here it's הפה שאסר הוא
הפה שהתיר. ha'peh she'asar hu ha'peh she'hitir. It's more drastic, as the
גמרא Gemara will get to. So here רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua says
we do believe the guy. So therefore the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ומדתני
ומודה רבי יהושע. u'midtani u'modeh Rabi Yehoshua. אי אמרת בשלמא איירי רבן
גמליאל במודה, ei amrat bishlama ayri Rabban Gamliel b'modeh, if רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel concedes his point, he says, "Normally I say that we
believe the woman, and here I'm going to concede that we don't
believe the woman. I'm not going to call it a ברי ושמא."
bari v'shema. So שפיר, shapir, then it's good that רבי יהושע Rabi
Yehoshua will say, "Well normally I believe the guy who's originally in
possession of the money, you know, and here I'm going to believe
the guy who got the field from him. So I'll concede this
point. You concede that point, I'll concede this point. Everybody is giving
in a little." Okay, so far. That makes sense. So then there's
a structure to the
משנה, Mishnah, like a logical structure. אלא אי אמרת לא איירי רבן
גמליאל במודה, ela ei amrat lo ayri Rabban Gamliel b'modeh, but if
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel isn't conceding his point, meaning if the משנה
Mishnah here is not רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, if the משנה Mishnah
here is basically רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua and that's why you need
witnesses, that fundamentally רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel would disagree with this משנה,
Mishnah, maybe רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel would believe her, so this whole
משנה Mishnah is רבי יהושע. Rabi Yehoshua. So if you think this
whole משנה Mishnah is רבי יהושע, Rabi Yehoshua,
so לא איירי רבן גמליאל במודה, lo ayri Rabban Gamliel b'modeh, רבי
יהושע למאן מודה? Rabi Yehoshua l'man modeh?
What makes sense, how does it make sense to say, "Oh, but
רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua concedes the following case"? The whole משנה Mishnah
was רבי יהושע. Rabi Yehoshua. So it makes more sense, all right
I know, the גמרא Gemara will say so, it makes more sense
to understand that the beginning of the משנה Mishnah is a case
of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel conceding that she does not win because
it's a ברי וברי, bari u'bari, and then we have a case
where רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua would concede that the also that the
guy who's coming to take the property away would win because it's
a הפה שאסר. ha'peh she'asar. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, מי סברת, mi savrat, so now it says I think what
Michael was trying to say, רבי יהושע אהאי פירקא קאי? Rabi Yehoshua
a'hai pirka ka'i? Who says רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua is conceding to
like, you know, a רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel in the beginning of
the משנה? Mishnah? You want to read the משנה Mishnah that רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel concedes this point because it's ברי וברי, bari u'bari,
and רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua concedes a different point of a הפה
שאסר. ha'peh she'asar. What makes you think that מודה רבי יהושע modeh
Rabi Yehoshua is going on the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of this
משנה? Mishnah? Okay and oh, since you רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel conceded,
I'm going to concede another point. So אהאי פירקא קאי? a'hai pirka
ka'i? No, אמיגו קאי ואפירקא קמא קאי. a'migo ka'i v'apirka kamma ka'i.
He's going back to an earlier statement from the previous פרק perek
about מיגו. migo. And he's saying, "You, רבן גמליאל," Rabban Gamliel, because
and now we're going to introduce a new factor. Why does רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel believe the woman? So we've been saying it's ברי
ושמא, bari v'shema, that's certainly been the strength of it, but you
might remember before that the גמרא Gemara also said that in some
cases there's a מיגו. migo. What per case in particular is there
going to be a מיגו? migo? The first case. The גמרא's Gemara
going to work its way backward through all the משניות mishnayos to
get to the first case, because the first case there was a
מיגו. migo. The first case, she said
that I was raped after the קידושין, kiddushin, and he said, "No,
you had basically, you know, you had consensual sex." So there she
could have made a stronger claim. Her claim could have been I
was like a מוכת עץ mukat etz or something. Saying she was
raped will invalidate her for a כהן, kohen, you know, if this
marriage ever ends and then she wants to marry a כהן, kohen,
it'll invalidate her. So there was a מיגו. migo. And רבי יהושע
Rabi Yehoshua was not impressed by that מיגו. migo. As רש"י Rashi
says, one reason not to be impressed by the מיגו migo is
maybe somebody is smart and knows how to work the system. Right?
So somebody figures, "If I say as מוכת עץ, mukat etz, I
won't win. I'll say I was raped and therefore at least I'm
going to win this case." So רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua wasn't impressed
by that מיגו. migo. But he is impressed by our case of
a הפה שאסר. ha'peh she'asar. A guy who just סתם stam says,
walks off the street and says, "This field, by the way, you
should know that I've been on for the last few years, this
field originally was your father's and I bought it from him," that's
stronger than a מיגו. migo. That's like a הפה שאסר. ha'peh she'asar.
He's introducing the whole case to begin with, so therefore obviously he's
going to be believed. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is
רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua when it says he concedes, doesn't have to
concede a, you know, in parallel to a רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
point in the beginning of our משנה. Mishnah. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
would concede that this is a ברי וברי, bari u'bari, and therefore
he's going to say that she doesn't win. Okay, I'll concede a
הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar case. No, this whole משנה Mishnah might not
be רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, it might all be רבי יהושע, Rabi
Yehoshua, but what רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua is saying is, "By the
way, the fact that earlier, the past פרק, perek, I rejected the
argument of מיגו, migo, I will concede a case where it's stronger
than just a מיגו. migo. I'll concede a case where it's a
הפה שאסר." ha'peh she'asar. Okay. So he might not be referring to
a concession of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel at the beginning of this
משנה, Mishnah, he might be going back to a debate that they
had in the previous פרק. perek.
What does the man say in this case when she's claiming the
כתובה, kesubah, הפה שאסר או הפה שהתיר? ha'peh she'asar o ha'peh she'hitir?
No, there's not הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar in the כתובה kesubah case.
The הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar is in the end of the משנה
Mishnah where he says, "I bought this field from him." your father.
And then the other guy says, huh, I didn't know what you're
talking about. So that's obviously he's introducing the whole case from scratch.
We'll get in a minute to what תוספות Tosafot says about that,
but רש"י Rashi says it's much stronger because he isn't even being,
he isn't even being like you know sued or anything. He isn't
being, you know nobody's coming to him with a טענה, taina, right?
He's just introducing the whole case. By the way, this field, you
know it once was your father's, I bought it from him. So
of course Rabbi Yehoshua would say in that case, I'll concede, that's
much stronger than a מיגו. migo. Yes.
But Rabbi Yehoshua doesn't hold by the concept of מיגו migo at
all ever?
Well, he might. But there are different degrees of מיגו. migo. So
first of all, one thing is called a מיגו להוציא, migo l'hotzi,
which is our case, which is a מיגו migo to take out
money, to extract money. And in the same way it's like for
example you don't go רוב, rov, אין הולכין בממון אחר הרוב, ein
holchin b'mamon achar ha'rov, you might need a higher
threshold when we say המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah
than just a מיגו. migo. That's number one. Number two is, the
fact that it's one thing to have a מיגו migo that if
I would have made this other claim I would have, I definitely
would have won, so you should believe me by this claim, right?
That's different than just, well I could have made a better, I
could have made a claim that would have been better but it
wouldn't necessarily have made me win. Meaning, for example, let's say I'm
trying to think of an example, but let's say, you know, you
say that that object is you know, this object I'm holding on
to you say it's yours. So if I were to say I
never bought it from you, let's just imagine, I'm not going to
go into the specific הלכה. halacha. Let's say, let's say you say
this coffee cup here, you say it's yours. I say if I
would have said I never bought it from you, I would have
been believed. Okay, but if I said I bought it from you
under certain circumstances, that claim by itself wouldn't be believed. But maybe
if I said I bought it from you under those circumstances you
should believe me because if I would have said I never bought
it from you then I totally would have won the case. That's
where my alternate claim would have clearly won the case and therefore
you should believe me when I make a different one because I
always could have made the claim that would have won the case.
The מיגו migo that we're talking about is not a מיגו migo
that by itself would have won the case, right? If I were
to say, if a woman would have said that it was מוכת
עץ muksah etz as opposed to a rape, that wouldn't have necessarily
won the case, you'll say it's not מוכת עץ. muksah etz. So
a מיגו migo that it would have been a better claim but
not a claim that would have won is different than a מיגו
migo when I could have said a claim that definitely would have
won. So there's so, good question, why does רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
reject מיגו? migo? So two things to acknowledge about these cases, number
one it's a מיגו להוציא, migo l'hotzi, that's a מיגו migo that's
trying to use as a basis of taking money away from somebody,
which normally there's a higher threshold. And number two, it's a מיגו
migo where the other claim wouldn't have on its own won, it
might have been a better claim but it wouldn't have won. Okay,
normally if the מיגו migo would have won, that's a different story.
And maybe רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel maybe רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua totally
rejects מיגו. migo. The way רש"י Rashi makes it sound is unless
it's a פה שאסר, peh she'assar, unless the guy is introducing the
whole scenario on his own, then but if he's being, he's if
he's being like sued and challenged then any response we maybe he
just says then whatever I just don't believe מיגו, migo, then you're
just trying to work the system. Okay. So it could be he
completely rejects it, but there could be specific reasons that make this
מיגו migo weaker, it's against, it's trying to take out money and
the other claim wouldn't have wouldn't have won on its own. Okay.
So now let's take a look. So that's what he's conceding. He's
not conceding to a concession רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said in the
beginning of the משנה, mishnah, that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says well
I'll concede by ברי וברי, barri v'barri, and he says well I'll
concede by פה שאסר. peh she'assar. No, maybe the whole beginning of
the משנה mishnah is רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, but רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua saying it's by the way, you know the debate we had
last פרק perek where I rejected מיגו? migo? I'll concede in the
case when it's better than a מיגו, migo, when it's a case
when it's a פה שאסר. peh she'assar. Okay. So אמיגו קאי, ובפרקין
קמא קאי. Amigo kai, v'pirkin kama kai.
And he's going on the earlier פרק. perek. So אהיי, ahai, which
case in the earlier פרק perek was a מיגו migo that he
rejected? אילימא הא, ilima ha, the following, now we're going to work
back through the משניות mishnayot from the last back to the earliest
and it's going to be interesting because this is like we had
to wait to the second פרק perek to see this but now
the גמרא's Gemara going to conceptualize the issues in the different משניות
mishnayot and tell us which ones are bigger חידוש chiddush than the
others. So let's take a look. היא שמעוברת, hi she'muberet, ואמרו לה,
מה טיבו של עובר זה, v'amru lah, mah tivo shel ubar zeh,
she's pregnant, what's the status of this baby? מאיש פלוני וכהן הוא,
m'ish ploni v'kohen hu, oh I had sex with this man but
he's okay, he's a כהן. kohen. רבן גמליאל ורבי אליעזר אומרים נאמנת,
Rabban Gamliel v'Rabbi Eliezer omrim ne'emenet, she's believed. רבי יהושע אומר לא
מפי אנו חיים, Rabbi Yehoshua omer lo mipi anu chayim, no we
don't live based on her say so, right? No, I guess מפי
mipi as opposed to פה שאסר פה שהתיר, peh she'assar peh she'ittir,
here we're not going to live by what she said. התם, hatam,
so what מיגו migo is there there? מאי מיגו איכא? mai migo
ika? הרי כריסה בין שיניה, harei kreisa bein shineha, what מיגו migo
is there?
Her stomach is between her teeth, so obviously she had sex with
some guy, so what else is she supposed to claim? She's claiming
the best thing she could claim. Oh yeah, you all know I
had sex, and I'm going to say the guy was a totally
good guy. So there's no מיגו, migo, there's no better claim she
could make. אלא אהא, ella aha, fine, this case. והיא מדברת עם
אחד, vehi m'daberet im echad,
and they saw speaking to a guy, ואמרו לה מה טיבו של
איש זה, v'amru lah mah tivo shel ish zeh, so they saw
her speaking to a guy, they said hey what's the story with
that guy you were talking to or maybe slept with? So she
says איש פלוני וכהן הוא, ish ploni v'kohen hu, yeah it was
the guy I slept with but he was a good guy, he
was a כהן. kohen. רבן גמליאל ורבי אליעזר אומרים נאמנת, Rabban Gamliel
v'Rabbi Eliezer omrim ne'emenet, she's believed. רבי יהושע אומר לא מפי אנו
חיים, Rabbi Yehoshua omer lo mipi anu chayim, we don't believe her.
So התם, מאי מיגו איכא? hatam mai migo ika, What else could
she have claimed? הניחא לזעירי, ha nicha l'Zeiri, it's
actually according to זעירי Zeiri she could have had an alternate claim.
דאמר מאי מדברת נסתרה, d'amar mai m'daberet nistera, according to זעירי Zeiri
all it meant is that she went into seclusion with the guy.
So מיגו דאי בעיא אמרה לא נסתרתי, migo d'i ba'i amra lo
nistarti, if she... he could have said I never had sex with
him, that definitely would have been a better claim, better claim in
terms of your own sort of standing in the community to say
you didn't have sex with him, and better claim because presumably you
would be believed. How is anybody supposed to know you had sex?
So if you said you wouldn't have had sex, you would have
totally been believed. That would have been a better claim. And she
became pregnant? No, the second case. The case of
מדברת. medaberet. Okay, וקאמרה נבעלתי v'kamra nivalti and she says she had
sex, מהימנא, mehemnah, so she would be believed. That would be a
מיגו. migo. And if רבן גמליאל... Rabban Gamliel... and that would make
sense. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is saying that מיגו migo I don't
accept. When she could have said she had sex and but she
concedes she she could have said she didn't have sex, she concedes
she did. I'm not going to accept that מיגו. migo. הפה שאסר
ha'peh she'asar I'll accept, but that's a מיגו migo I won't accept.
Okay, that's a big חידוש. chiddush. Okay, wait a minute. Okay, אלא
לרב אשי, ela l'Rav Ashi, דאמר מאי המדבר נבעלה, d'amar mai hamidaber
nivala, but according to רב אשי Rav Ashi that means that she
actually had sex and that isn't debated, we all know she had
sex. So מאי מיגו איכא? mai migo ika? So what else? So
everybody knows she had sex, so she's saying the guy was a
good guy. There's no מיגו, migo, there's no better claim. So so
far, those two cases, if both of them are that we know
she had sex, there was no מיגו. migo. So it's no חידוש
chiddush for רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua to say I don't believe her.
However, if one of the cases was we don't know she had
sex and she conceded that she did, that's a חידוש. chiddush. That
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says I won't believe her even though she
could have said she didn't have sex, but I will believe in
a total case of הפה שאסר. ha'peh she'asar. Okay, so that would
be one way to frame it, but that's only if you assume
that one of those cases was that we don't know that she
had sex.
Yes. But I don't understand why these two cases are not or
cannot be framed as a as הפה שאסר, ha'peh she'asar, שהפה שאסר.
she'hapeh she'asar.
Well, that's going to be well first of all we have to
get a מיגו. migo.
She's not she's not okay, yeah.
Okay, so the question is is why is the case when she
concedes that she that she had sex when we don't know that
she did, why isn't that הפה שאסר? ha'peh she'asar? So the גמרא's
Gemara going to get to it. How is מיגו migo different?
Is it because they brought a טענה ta'ana against her?
Okay, yes. So we're going to get to it. But the question's
going to be why is מיגו migo different than הפה שאסר? ha'peh
she'asar? But first we have to establish there's a מיגו. migo. So
the first thing we're saying is there is no מיגו migo in
those cases. We know she had sex. What else is she supposed
to say? So if she could have said she didn't have sex,
she has a מיגו, migo, but that's not necessarily the case. All
right, so let's keep on going. ואלא הא, v'ela ha,
היא אומרת מוכת עץ אני, hee omeret mukat etz ani, והוא אומר
לא כי אלא דרוסת איש. v'hu omer lo ki ela drusat ish.
She says, yes I wasn't a virgin but that's because I had
some injury, and he says no because you had sex. רבן גמליאל
ורבי אליעזר אומרים נאמנת, Rabban Gamliel v'Rabbi Eliezer omrim ne'emenet, she's believed.
רבי יהושע אומר לא מפינו אנו חיים, Rabbi Yehoshua omer lo mipinu
anu chayim, no, she's not believed. So התם hatam, מאי מיגו איכא,
mai migo ika? what else could she have claimed other than that
she was a מוכת עץ? mukat etz? So let's take a look.
Did she have a better claim? בשלמא לרבי אליעזר, bishlama l'Rabbi Eliezer,
דאמר במנה ולא כלום, d'amar b'maneh v'lo klum,
so according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says when he said
I thought you were a בתולה betulah and it turned out you
had sex, you get zero. And she says no, I should have
told you, I didn't tell you, but I was a מוכת עץ,
mukat etz, but since obviously there was a certain amount of misunderstanding
you get a hundred. Okay, remember that was one way of framing
it between a hundred and zero. So then she has a מיגו
migo because she could have made a claim that would have entitled
her to 200. Okay, מיגו
דאי בעיא אמרה מוכת עץ אני תחתיך, migo d'ee ba'ya amra mukat
etz ani tachteach, she could have said I had an injury after
the קידושין, kiddushin, not before the קידושין, kiddushin, and that would have
entitled her to 200. דאית לה מאתים, d'it lah matayim, and she
could have said I'm entitled to 200. Yes, I wasn't a virgin
on my wedding night because I had an injury after the
קידושין. kiddushin. וקאמרה מעיקרא, v'kamra me'ikara, and then she said actually I
had this injury before the קידושין, kiddushin, דלית לה אלא מנה, d'leit
lah ela maneh, and therefore she's conceding
she only gets a hundred. מהימנא, mehemnah, that's a מיגו. migo. I
could have made a claim that would have entitled her to 200
and she made a claim of a hundred.
אלא לרבי יוחנן, ela l'Rabbi Yochanan, דאמר במאתים ומנה, d'amar b'matayim u'maneh,
but according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that says if he assumed
she was a בתולה betulah and it turned out she was a
מוכת עץ, mukat etz, she gets 200. So she's claiming 200. And
if it turned out she was a בעולה beulah she gets a
hundred. So their debate is between 200 and a hundred. So her
claim that she was a מוכת עץ mukat etz from before the
wedding, that's the strongest claim she can make. So מאי מיגו איכא,
mai migo ika, there's no מיגו. migo. So so far it's possible
there was a מיגו migo in two of those cases depending on
how you set up the scenario. If it could have been that
she went into private and she conceded she had sex and she
didn't have to concede, that was a מיגו. migo. It's possible she's
only asking a claim for a hundred because of מוכת עץ mukat
etz and she could have said a מוכת עץ תחתיך mukat etz
tachteach and could have been a claim for 200. So it's possible
two of those cases are מיגו, migo, but it's possible based on
how you interpret those cases neither of them have a מיגו. migo.
But it's finally going to be the last or the first of
the משניות mishnayot that everybody concedes has a מיגו. migo.
So מאי מיגו איכא mai migo ika because she's making the best
claim she could.
Because she's making the best claim, exactly. So אלא הא, ela ha,
it's the first of those משניות mishnayot that everybody concedes has a
מיגו. migo. What is it? הנושא את האשה ולא מצא לה בתולים,
hanosei et ha'isha v'lo matza lah betulim, so she wasn't a virgin.
היא אומרת משארסתני נאנסתי ונסתחפה שדהו. hee omeret mishearastani ne'enasti v'nistachfa sadehu.
She says, I was raped after the marriage. והוא אומר לא כי
אלא עד שלא ארסתיך, v'hu omer lo ki ela ad shelo arastich,
no, you had sex before the marriage. רבן גמליאל ורבי אליעזר נאמנת.
Rabban Gamliel v'Rabbi Eliezer ne'emenet. רבי אליעזר אומר לא מפינו אנו חיים.
Rabbi Eliezer omer lo
mipinu anu chayim. דמיגו, d'migo, now that case clearly she has a
מיגו. migo. Because if she's saying she was raped after the marriage,
after the קידושין, kiddushin, she's saying she's פסול pasul to a כהן,
kohen, and she could have made a lot of other claims. She
could have said מוכת עץ, mukat etz, she could have said it
was. you know, so therefore אלא, ella, ואי בעית אימא מוכת עץ
אני תחתיך. v'ee ba'it eima mukat etz ani tachtayich. She could have
said I was a מוכת עץ mukat etz afterwards which would have
been after the קידושין kiddushin which would have entitled her to 200
and would not have invalidated her for a כהן. kohen. דלא פסלה
נפשה מכהונה d'lo pasla nafsha mikehuna would not have invalidated her from
a כהן. kohen. וקאמרה נאנסתי ופסלה נפשה מכהונה v'ka'amra ne'enasti v'pasla nafsha
mikehuna
and she's invalidating herself so clearly there certainly everybody would concede if
not in three out of the four cases at least one of
the four cases she has a מיגו. migo. She could have made
a better claim. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua still saying I don't
care, I'm not impressed. Okay. וקאמרה ופסלה מכהונה ומשום הכי קאמר רבן
גמליאל דמהימנא. v'ka'amra v'pasla mikehuna uvishum hachi ka'amar Rabban Gamliel d'meheimna.
And therefore רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says she's believed. Now is that's
the question about רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, whether רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
needs the מיגו migo or not? Because you'll remember one of the
cases right about the case about we know she slept with a
guy she's pregnant and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel believes her, there's no
מיגו migo in that case, right? Some of the cases the גמרא
Gemara said might not be a מיגו. migo. So רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel believes her because of her ברי bari and some of the
times that ברי bari is even backed up with a מיגו. migo.
Okay. רש״י Rashi also adds that another reason right remember that was
that whole question is רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel just because of ברי
bari or does he need something else? So if he needs something
else רש״י Rashi points out even in times he doesn't have a
מיגו migo you know what he has in all those times?
חזקה, chazaka, a חזקה chazaka that she's a כשרה koshera that she
didn't have you know that she didn't do something forbidden of this
woman that she didn't sleep with a guy that's forbidden to her,
חזקת הגוף. chezkat haguf. So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel has got her
ברי bari plus something else, plus a מיגו migo maybe plus her
חזקה, chazaka, חזקת הגוף. chezkat haguf. That's what רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
has got. That's why he's going to believe her.
What's the ברי bari here?
That she's saying I'm she's saying I know why I'm not a
virgin.
He's just guessing she's making
she's making a definite claim. ברי ושמא bari v'shema about the claims,
not about the objective reality. Okay. So she's got her ברי bari
plus her מיגו. migo. That's why רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel believes her.
ומשום הכי קאמר רבן גמליאל דמהימנא. uvishum hachi ka'amar Rabban Gamliel d'meheimna.
So she's got her ברי, bari, she's got her מיגו, migo, he
believes her. ואמר רבי יהושע לרבן גמליאל. v'amar Rabbi Yehoshua l'Rabban Gamliel.
So therefore way back in the first פרק perek רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel is saying she's a ברי bari and she's got a מיגו
migo I'm going to believe her. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua think
about the power of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua statement. He's saying even
though the guy's a שמא shema and even though she's got a
מיגו migo I'm not going to believe her. A ברי bari against
a שמא shema even a ברי bari plus a מיגו migo against
a שמא shema I'm not going to believe her. So רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua is not impressed with מיגו. migo. And then comes along
this פרק, perek, ואמר רבי יהושע לרבן גמליאל בהאי מיגו דהכא מודינא
לך בההוא מיגו דהתם פליגינא עליך. v'amar Rabbi Yehoshua l'Rabban Gamliel behai
migo d'hacha modina lach behahu migo d'hatam peligina alach. So the מיגו
migo here when he says this field was never you know this
field that I'm on it usually it once was your father's okay
in this because I could have shut up, בהאי מיגו דהכא מודינא
לך. behai migo d'hacha modina lach. That I'll concede. בההוא מיגו דהתם
פליגינא עליך. behahu migo d'hatam peligina alach. And the מיגו migo back
there that's when I disagreed with you. I'll agree here. So this
was a nice way of reviewing the earlier debate, reminding us that
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel has a ברי bari and a שמא shema
plus a מיגו migo and that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua even rejects
the מיגו migo even in a case where the guy's only on
a שמא. shema. So now we want to understand what makes this
case stronger. מכדי michdi says the גמרא Gemara one minute let's take
a look. האי מיגו והאי מיגו. hai migo v'hai migo. That was
a מיגו migo over there, she could have made a better claim.
Here was a מיגו, migo, he didn't have to admit that the
field originally belonged to the other guy. מאי
שנא האי מיגו מהאי מיגו. mai shena hai migo mehai migo. Why
is this case of הפה שאסר hapeh she'asar stronger than the מיגו
migo over there where she could have made a better claim? So
the גמרא Gemara says הכא אין שור שחוט לפניך התם הרי שור
שחוט לפניך. hacha ein shor shachut lefanecha hatam harei shor shachut lefanecha.
Here there's no slaughtered ox in front of you, there there's a
slaughtered ox in front of you. Okay. So besides of course the
imagery about the slaughtered ox and the blood running from the ox
and the בתולים betulim and all of those cases, once again a
very bloody type of an imagery. What does this metaphor mean? So
the metaphor רש״י Rashi says the debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot is very important. How do you read רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua?
רש״י Rashi says here nobody came to this guy. Everybody this the
the this
you know ראובן Reuven comes to שמעון Shimon and says by the
way this field I've been on used to belong to your father.
שמעון Shimon never approached ראובן. Reuven. שמעון Shimon never said give me
back that field, that's my field or anything. שמעון Shimon had no
was clueless. So there was no טענה ta'ana right there was nobody
was litigating, nobody was suing him. So in that case nobody is
pushing me against the wall and demanding a response and I just
come forward and concede something, of course I'm believed. I didn't have
to say anything. I could have just gone on my daily business.
So מיגו דאי בעי שתיק migo d'ee ba'i shatik is the way
some אחרונים achronim say it, which is like I could have just
been completely silent. So when I am offering the information, of course
I'm believed, right? Why else why shouldn't I be believed? I could
have just shut up. I could have said absolutely nothing. That's the
way רש״י Rashi explains it. I don't know. Okay. So תוספות Tosafot
תוספות Tosafot doesn't agree. תוספות Tosafot says no, this case the guy
is coming and saying give me back that field, that field was
my father's, you stole it from me. And he says yes, I
concede it was your father's but I bought it from him. Okay.
So that's a good question. How is it different? In both cases
the guy's being like you know charged with, not charged with whatever
you know, but sued, he's being there's a טענה ta'ana against him.
The difference is, no, the difference is, in one case, there's evidence
that needs to be answered for. In another case, there's no evidence
that needs to be answered for. In one case, there's the fact
that you weren't a virgin. And that's not debated. Whatever it was,
there was no blood on the sheets. For whatever reason, that was
not debated. That was seen as that was concrete evidence. Okay. So
now, you've got some explaining to do. If you've got some explaining
to do, the fact that I, well, I could have said a
better claim. I mean, already the already like I'm on the defensive.
I'm in a weaker position. As Rashi רש"י Rashi says, even if
I've got a migo מיגו migo maybe I know how to work
the system. But in another case, there's no evidence. I could say,
I don't know what the hell you're talking about. It was your
father's? I never saw you before in my life. I never saw
your father before in my life. Right? I don't have anything that
needs to be explained. So while I need to answer your claim,
the answer could have been what's called in as the acronym la-hadam
להד"ם. la-hadam. Lo hayu devarim me'olam לא היו דברים מעולם. Lo hayu
devarim me'olam. Like, I don't know what that you're talking about. So
when I could have said that, so I don't have to explain
any evidence, I could have said you're making it all up, then
my when I make a claim, the fact that I could have
said that you're making it all up, that's a better migo מיגו
migo that I could have just said, you know, but but if
I if I have to explain the evidence, one explanation as opposed
to another explanation, that he would not hold of the migo מיגו.
migo. And Tosfos תוספות Tosfos says that's the image of shor shachut
lefanecha שור שחוט לפניך. shor shachut lefanecha. If you have a dead
cow, there's no way you could say the cow was alive. Okay?
It's sort of like the reverse of the Monty Python, right? No,
there was the dead parrot skit, but then the "I'm not dead
yet" skit. Anyway. Okay. So yes, it's alive. Of course it's not
alive. You have to explain how did it die? Maybe you'll come
up with some reasonable explanation, but there's a dead cow here, you
got to explain it. In the other, there's no way you could
say it's alive. In the other case, you could say there's a
living cow walking around somewhere. What do I know? There's nothing evidence
there's no evidence that has to be controverted or that has to
be explained. So that's a big debate of Rashi רש"י Rashi Tosfos
תוספות Tosfos whether Rabbi Yehoshua רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua only has his
case when the person when he's not being attacked, or he'll have
his he'll admit that the guy is believed even when he's being
attacked, if his alternative could have if he had the opportunity to
say you're making it all up. Yes.
In the seifer סיפא seifer when there's eidim עדים eidim then he's
not believed. Is that because of the same principle?
What do you mean about eidim עדים eidim that she went when
to the-?
In the mishna משנה mishna why the migo מיגו-?
migo
Oh, right, because then there's because then it's shor shachut שור שחוט.
shor shachut. Then there's actually evidence. We know it was the father's.
You have to explain how it got into your hands. Okay. So
now what we have is that Rabban Gamliel רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
concedes the case of bari ve-bari ברי וברי. bari ve-bari. He only
made had the guy win because he had because the guy had
the woman because she had a bari ברי bari maybe plus a
migo מיגו migo plus a chazaka חזקה, chazaka, whatever. But if it's
like a bari and a bari ברי וברי, bari ve-bari, even though
her bari ברי bari is a little bit stronger because of the
rov רוב, rov, but if it's a bari and a bari ברי
וברי, bari ve-bari, Rabban Gamliel רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel concedes that she
doesn't win. And Rabbi Yehoshua רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua concedes that a
person with a pesha asar הפה שאסר pesha asar does win as
opposed to a migo מיגו. migo. And what's the pesha asar הפה
שאסר? pesha asar? The pesha asar הפה שאסר pesha asar is either
that the guy wasn't even making any claim against him, or the
guy was making a claim but there was no evidence that needed
to be answered for. Okay.
And the shor shachut שור שחוט shor shachut in in the case
of the woman is the ein lah betulim אין לה בתולים. ein
lah betulim. That's the shor shachut שור שחוט.
shor shachut. Right. And for some reason she could not say you're
making it all up. Again, maybe it was the case with the
sheets. Okay. That's interesting. We went through the whole perek פרק perek
and in all those mishnayot משניות mishnayot and in all the "he
said, she said," she never said, "Uh, you're making it all up."
Actually, we had some beraitas ברייתות beraitas that that had. Remember there
was a beraita ברייתא beraita that they came to Rebbe רבי Rebbe
and he said, and she said, "Actually, betula ani בתולה אני betula
ani or betula hayiti בתולה הייתי," betula hayiti, and then they checked
the sheet and they did some their various things. In the beraitas
ברייתות beraitas we had some scenarios where she actually said no, actually
I was a virgin. But in the mishna משנה, mishna, somehow that's
taken for granted that she wasn't a virgin and the only question
is how do you explain that? Okay. So maybe it was the
case where somehow they had the sheets and the sheets made it
clear and there was no type of a way to have said
it you're making it all up. Okay. But if you could say
you're making it all up, then obviously the story could be very
different. Okay, so now the gemara גמרא gemara says like this: Ve-kivan
de-rov nashim betulot nisos וכיון דרוב נשים בתולות נישאות, Ve-kivan de-rov nashim
betulot nisos,
one minute the gemara גמרא gemara says, if it's really true that
the majority of women get married, it's a first marriage, Ki leka
eidim mai havei כי ליכא עדים מאי הוי? Ki leka eidim mai
havei? Why not go by the majority? Okay. This was what Michael
was asking before. Now, if you take a look at the tiny
little Tosfos תוספות, Tosfos, Ki leka eidim mai havei כי ליכא עדים
מאי הוי, Ki leka eidim mai havei, Tosfos תוספות Tosfos says Le-Rav
parich de-islei hochan de-mamon achar ha-rov לרב פריך דאית ליה הולכין בממון
אחר הרוב. Le-Rav parich de-islei hochan de-mamon achar ha-rov. Okay. There's a
big debate of Rav רב Rav and Shmuel שמואל Shmuel whether rov
רוב rov is a good enough basis to take money out of
the person that's in possession of it. Okay. Normally you say ha-motzi
mi-chavero alav ha-re'aya המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה, ha-motzi mi-chavero alav ha-re'aya, it
requires a higher standard. But there is a position of Rav רב
Rav that sometimes you would go by rov רוב. rov. It's a
question whether Rav רב Rav would say in a case like this,
but anyway, that's what the gemara גמרא gemara wants to know. If
it's really true that most women get married and then why not
believe her or maybe even at least according to Rabban Gamliel רבן
גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, why not have it back her up and why
not have her win? Okay. So, so the gemara גמרא gemara says,
Amar Ravina mishum de-ika le-meimar rov nashim betulot nisos אמר רבינא משום
דאיכא למימר רוב נשים בתולות נישאות. Amar Ravina mishum de-ika le-meimar rov
nashim betulot nisos. It's true. Most women do have their marriage is
a first marriage. U-mi'ut almanot ומיעוט אלמנות, U-mi'ut almanot, and a smaller
percentage they're widows or divorcees. Ve-chol ha-nisos betula yesh lah kol וכל
הנישאות בתולה יש לה קול, Ve-chol ha-nisos betula yesh lah kol, but
there's something that counteracts the presumption that she was it was a
first marriage. Because anytime it's a first marriage, there's a lot of
publicity about it. I mean there's a better word than publicity, there's
a lot of knowledge about it, a lot of awareness about it,
right? A first wedding, you got the whole engraved invitation, you invite
three hundred people. So there's more awareness of the first wedding. וזו
הואיל ואין לה קול איתרע לה רובא. Vezu hoil ve'ein lah kol
itra lah ruba.
This one, if there you can't find any witnesses, right? And no
so therefore nobody remembers and nobody knows about it, that undermines the
likelihood that it was a wedding. There was a likelihood but it
wasn't by pure percentages. But if there were if it had first
wedding, but it had been a first wedding, we would have almost
most likely have found people that would have remembered. Oh yeah, I
remember that.
Depends where you are. Suppose they moved from מדינת הים, Medinat Hayam,
so you wouldn't be able to say that. That's true, that's true.
You could have some scenarios. Okay, so so the גמרא Gemara says
one minute. So that's why we're back in a balance situation. אי
כל הנישאות בתולות יש להן קול Ee kol hanisot betulot yesh lahen
kol one minute. If every time there's a first wedding, there's always
like a wide awareness of it, כי אתו עדי מאי הוה הני
סהדי שקרי נינהו. ki atu edi mai hava hanei sahedi shikrei ninhu.
So I don't get it. So...
You mean
this is weaker than the קול. kol. They could lie. Right.
If there was no קול, kol, apparently it means if there was
no קול, kol, so apparently even if one minute,
right, it's a funny idea because how do we measure the קול?
kol? Even if the witnesses came, right, why don't why aren't we
more aware? I mean I misstated it before. It's not just if
there's a קול kol then there should be witnesses. If there was
a קול kol we should be aware of it, right? How is
it that this guy state of course how do we remember from
twenty years ago? I've been always saying twenty years, but it could
be two years, could be one year. So how could it be
that this has come to the court and we don't remember that
it was a first wedding? So that counteracts the likelihood that it's
a first wedding. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but if that's
true, then even if witnesses come, say the fact that there's no
awareness of this should even counteract the witnesses. Say what? I know.
It's it's very funny, like how do you measure קול kol anyway?
And how many anyway... Witnesses in the whole
town. I understand, I understand. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא ela
the problem is that it says כל הנישאות בתולות יש להן קול.
kol hanisot betulot yesh lahen kol. But the problem I think that
we have is that it might be that there always was a
קול, kol, but that doesn't mean that the קול kol is always
remembered and persists and how do you know and whose memory do
you go by if they're not testifying to it if you know.
It's a funny issue. Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אלא אמר רבינא...
ela amar Ravina... Same with real estate also, you could say the
same thing. Twenty years later, who remembers? But that's just the way
that's just becomes the rule. Yeah, but a קול kol is a
קול, kol, you know.
Well what do you mean by real estate who remembers? Where where
do you go by קול kol by by real estate?
חזקה. chazaka. Yeah, but that's evidence of of like of being on
the land. That's not that's not memory of like. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, so it's a funny idea. The assumption
that that קול kol would still be would still persist and that
how we would be able to know we had the קול, kol,
who's remembering the קול kol without without being a witness to the
event. Anyway, אלא אמר רבינא רוב הנישאות בתולות יש להן קול. ela
amar Ravina rov hanisot betulot yesh lahen kol. Fine.
Most of the time there'll be a קול. kol. Maybe a קול
kol means that the קול kol will persist. Okay. וזו הואיל ואין
לה קול איתרע לה רובא. Vezu hoil ve'ein lah kol itra lah
ruba. We're not saying all the time. All right, so fine. You
have a רוב rov that it was a first wedding, but counteracting
the רוב rov is if there really had been a first wedding,
we probably still would have remembered it. Not a hundred percent. If
witnesses come we'll go by the witnesses.
But it's so there's probably we would have remembered it had it
been a first wedding, since we don't remember it that balances the
likelihood that it was a first wedding.
So basically we don't need a witness, so we can say you
know so the husband is saying that okay you're
not a בתולה betula when I married you, then some guy says
'yeah you know what but I remember reading about it in the
New York Times, I don't have the New York Times in front
of me and you know and
will that be okay?' Yeah, so that's the question who measures the
קול? kol? No, because then that's just like an עד אחד ed
echad that's an עד מפי עד, ed mipi ed, right? A קול
kol means that there's some general awareness of it. Again, I don't
know how we're supposed to have measured that קול.
kol. So specifically to say then I saw בהינומא behinuma her so
her going out בהינומא, behinuma, that's...
Yes, yes. That's direct evidence. I mean it's not direct evidence about
her personal physical status, but it's direct evidence about about something concretely
that happened during the wedding. Yes.
He should
have hired a photographer.
Ha! Hired a photographer. He would have kept the negatives. There you
go. All right, there you go. Perfect. Anyway, all right. Whatever it
so the גמרא Gemara basically says that according to רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel why not use the רוב? rov? And it says 'yeah, but
you know the רוב rov is counterbalanced by the fact that there's
not a strong memory about this situation, okay?' And that leaves open
the possibility that she's not considered to be that witnesses obviously could
could prove her case, but it does not give her a presumption
of being correct. Okay?
So the goal is to get the כתובה.
ketubah. Yeah. And that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to actually get
right now. Okay. אם יש לה עדים שיצאת בהינומא. Im yesh lah
edim sheyatsata behinuma. Now if there're witnesses that she went out with
the whole like bedecked and in this whole like wedding chariot or
whatever, so ולחוש דלמא מפקא עדים בהאי בי דינא וגביה והדר מפקא
לכתובה בהאי בי דינא וגביה בה. veleichush dilma mafka edim behai bei
dina vegavya vehadar mafka leketuba behai bei dina vegavya bah. Okay. One
minute. Maybe she's hiding the כתובה, ketubah,
she'll use her witnesses that there was a first wedding, she'll collect
her כתובה, ketubah, and then she'll go to another court in another
city or whatever it will be, they'll move or whatever the case
might be. And then she'll extract her כתובה. kesuvah. What's protecting the
husband's interests once he pays this if there's no written כתובה? kesuvah?
So he doesn't get a receipt or something?
She'll give him a receipt. So let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says, וגביא. אמר רבי אבא זאת אומרת כותבין שובר. v'gavya.
Amar Rabbi Abba zos omeres kotvin shovar. This tells you you write
a receipt. Now, what's what's the big חידוש? chiddush? So the big
חידוש chiddush is, is why should the guy who paid out the
money have the responsibility to hold on to his receipt? Okay, if
I basically, you know, borrowed money from you, and then I paid
it off, and my debt is done, what, I have to hold
on to that receipt for forever? Because you might come ahead and
take out a שטר shtar against me? So there's one opinion that
says, yeah, that's the way the system works. You know, if the
guy's got a שטר shtar and he can give it back, tear
it up, but if not, you hold on to the receipt and
you got to hold on to it. But another opinion in a
in a גמרא, Gemara, you know, not here, but in, you know,
elsewhere says that that's not fair. It's not fair to demand that
I hold on to the receipt. So therefore what we'll say is,
if you have the שטר shtar to give back, give back the
שטר shtar and we'll tear it up. And if you don't have
a שטר shtar to give back, you can't collect your debt. You
can't collect your debt without a שטר. shtar. The fact that you
might still be holding on to that שטר shtar somewhere and waiting
for the guy to lose his receipt, that's not tolerable. So we
won't have a system of receipts and we'll say, if you don't
have a שטר shtar to produce, then the guy doesn't have to
pay back his debt, even if you can prove he borrowed the
money. Okay, so that's a different way of running a system, right?
Each one comes with a cost. One comes to a cost with
the loaner and one comes to with a cost to the to
the creditor. Okay, so do you demand that the person hold on
to receipts? Or at least say that that will be there are
times where that will be necessary? Do you say no, you've got
to hold on to your שטר, shtar, and if you lost your
שטר, shtar, you lose it. Okay, even if you can prove that
the guy borrowed the money. So it says, look, you see that
this shows that we do have a system of writing receipts, because
we let her collect without her כתובה. kesuvah. Okay, so that's pretty
good evidence. So the גמרא Gemara says, רב פפא אמר במקום שאין
כותבין כתובה עסקינן. Rav Pappa amar bimakom she'ein kotvin kesuvah askinan. No,
we're talking about a case where they don't write the שטרות. shtaros.
So meaning, even if I would concede that in general when a
document is written, all the responsibility falls on the person who has
the document, and if he loses his שטר, shtar, he cannot collect,
if there's a place where there are no שטרות shtaros written, you
know, where all the debts are done, let's say, with witnesses but
not with documents, okay, or here in the case where they never
wrote out a כתובה. kesuvah. It was just the standard obligation based
on what the rabbis said, we never wrote out a document. In
that case, of course you've got to have a system of receipts
because there's no alternative. Okay, so our debate is in scenarios where
the practice of the place is to have, you know, documents of,
you know, of debt or documents of כתובה kesuvah or whatever. There
we could say, no receipt, your responsibility to hold on to the
to produce the document. But if it's not a place where they
write those documents, then clearly there's going to be a system of
receipts.
Why wouldn't they write one because you want to
protect the woman and all that? That's a good question. Okay, we'll
see that later. That's the position of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Of course that's the place where they didn't write the כתובה, kesuvah,
what happens?
Produce witnesses whether it was a first wedding or not and collect
the appropriate amount.
So then then then it's much more likely then for him to
be able to make claims? That's the problem. What? I mean then
then that disadvantages her?
Of course it disadvantages her, right. Yeah. So for but whatever, my
question was
because, you know, I thought they said should...
Okay, but that's a מחלוקת, machlokes, that's a מחלוקת machlokes about whether
we say that. Okay, so anyway, but right, obviously you would not
want it would be you would be in a severe disadvantage to
be in a place where you where you did not have any
any paper documents. Okay, anyway, so that's the answer. במקום שאין כותבין
כתובה עסקינן. Bimakom she'ein kotvin kesuvah askinan. And therefore we're going to
go ahead and obviously allow for receipts to be written in that
scenario. Okay, ואיכא דמתני לה אברייתא. v'ika d'masni lah abraysa. Some have
this debate of רב פפא Rav Pappa and רבי אבא Rabbi Abba
not on the משנה Mishnah but on the ברייתא. Brayta. Here's what
the ברייתא Brayta said, it's almost exactly the case of our משנה,
Mishnah, but it's a little bit more explicit. אבדה כתובתה, Ibda kesubasah,
if she lost her כתובה, kesuvah, or this might be אבדה ibda
more might be like destroyed it, okay, הטמינה כתובתה, hitmina kesubasah,
or if she hid it, secreted it away, או נשרפה כתובתה, o
nisrepha kesubasah, or got destroyed, burned. Then so in all those cases
she has no כתובה kesuvah to produce, how do you prove whether
it's a first wedding or not? So here are the types of
testimony that would prove that it was a first wedding. רקדו לפניה
שחקו לפניה. Rakdu l'phaneha sachaku l'phaneha. First of all, did they have
the wedding dances? Okay, it's very interesting. We get a little insight
into the practice they had at the wedding. So if they had,
you know, did they do שטיק shtick at the wedding, right? Did
they have a whole big like dancing in front of the כלה,
kallah, guess what tomorrow's דף daf is going to be? כיצד מרקדין
לפני הכלה. Keitzad merakdin liphnei hakallah. So anyway, yeah. So anyway, so,
you know, did they do שטיק, shtick, שחקו לפניה, sachaku l'phaneha, right?
That would be a proof that they only do that at first
wedding.
Making more money at a second wedding?
Right. העבירו לפניה כוס של בשורה. Heviru l'phaneha kos shel besorah. Did
they pass in front of her a cup, a goblet of like
good well-wishes? We'll see what that is. או מפה של בתולים, O
mappa shel besulim, got
to love that one. They walked they did a whole dance with
her with with a bedsheet, which is the the bedsheet they were
going to use that night to to show whether or not she
was a virgin.
In that case it's כתובתה מאתים. Kesuvatah Masayim.
She
gets 200. So that was first of all more graphic in terms
of what types of things they might have done, but in terms
of the scenario, it says explicitly she destroyed or she hid or
it got or it was
or it was burned. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara clearly we started
with a כתובה Kesuvah and she can still collect, so it's a
place where they write a כתובה Kesuvah and she can still collect,
so it shows you that you would write a שובר Shovar even
in a place where you normally write out documents. So the
גמרא Gemara says וליחוש וליחוש דילמא מפקא עדים בהאי בי דינא וגביא
והדר מפקא לכתובתה בהאי בי דינא וגביא, Veleichosh veleichosh dilma mapka edim
behai bei dina vegavya vehadar mapka lekesuvatah behai bei dina vegavya, maybe
she'll pick out witnesses in this בית דין Beis Din and collect,
and then she'll pick out the כתובה Kesuvah in another בית דין
Beis Din and collect? בה אמר ליה אבא זו אומרת, Ba amar
lei Abba zo omeret, this tells you כותבין שובר Kotvin Shovar that
you'll write a receipt and that הבעל HaBaal will hold onto the
receipt even though it's a place where you write כתובות. Kesuvos. רב
פפא אמר במקום שאין כותבין כתובה עסקינן, Rav Pappa amar bemakom she'ein
kotvin kesuvah askinan, it's a place where they don't write out כתובות
Kesuvos and therefore, therefore we allow a system of receipts, but in
general we would not. So the גמרא Gemara says, how could you
say that? והא אבדה כתובתה קתני, Veha avdah kesuvatah katani, it says
that she lost or whatever destroyed her כתובה, Kesuvah, clearly there was
a כתובה, Kesuvah, or it says it got burned or it says
whatever. So the גמרא Gemara says, אבדה כתובתה קתני דכתב לה איהו.
Avdah kesuvatah katani dechasa lei ihu. Okay, it's a place where they
normally don't write כתובות, Kesuvos, so in this type of place we
have a system of receipts and it just so happened that he
wrote her the כתובה. Kesuvah. Okay, it doesn't mean it's אסור Assur
to write a כתובה, Kesuvah, he did it. But because it's a
place that doesn't, this place has receipts. And a place that generally
does, no receipts, you got to hold onto your document. And a
place that generally doesn't, there are receipts and it just so happened
that he actually in this place that doesn't, and therefore there are
receipts, he happened to write her a כתובה, Kesuvah, דכתב לה איהו.
Dechasa lei ihu. והא אבדה כתובתה קתני סוף סוף מפקא לה וגביא
בה? Veha avdah kesuvatah katani sof sof mapka la vegavya ba? So
I don't get it, but if so even if it is a
case where there actually was a written כתובה Kesuvah and she maybe
is and we don't know that it's destroyed, she said it's lost,
we even said maybe she even hid it away, how do we
go ahead
and deal with this situation? Maybe she's going to go ahead and
recollect. Okay, because because if you're going to say that there's no
receipts that are
done. Now of course the answer
is because in this case he isn't writing a כתובה Kesuvah so
therefore he's not going to have a receipt, but she might but
she might have written, we're saying we should worry for the case
that he might have written one.
Yeah, I'm not exactly getting this. Hold on one second, let me
just check רש"י Rashi one minute.
Yeah, I'm not exactly getting it.
Since since it's a מקום שאין כותבין, Makom she'ein kotvin, שאין כותבין,
She'ein kotvin,
oh,
yeah, no, I think what we're assuming is, no, no, no, because
I jumped ahead because I told you, no, that's right, because they
don't write receipts but there's always a way to prove,
one minute, one minute, one minute, one minute, and the
truth is
because in this case he happened
to write one.
Okay,
so I actually jumped ahead, I've been making a mistake. What I
told you what the גמרא Gemara is going to say later is
a problem by doing the whole דף Daf and I've incorporated it
earlier. The גמרא Gemara is later going to say that, you know,
in a place where they don't write or whatever and you have
no choice because there's no שטר, Shtar, there would be receipts. But
right now the גמרא Gemara isn't assuming that. Right now the גמרא
Gemara is assuming that if there's nothing written, you're not afraid that
she's going to produce a כתובה Kesuvah in another בית דין. Beis
Din. Now I don't understand why she hasn't to go ahead and
take the same עדים Edim and produce or different set of עדים.
Edim. There are a lot of people at the wedding, take one
set of עדים Edim to one בית דין, Beis Din, take one
set of עדים Edim to another בית דין. Beis Din. For some
reason, that we're not concerned about. We're only concerned about עדים Edim
in one בית דין Beis Din and a כתובה Kesuvah in the
next בית דין, Beis Din, okay? That somehow that will be treated
as completely different, nobody will know about it and whatnot. So therefore
until now when we've been answering the one who says that we
don't write receipts, so he says so what's the explanation about why
all this works? Well, all this works because and we're not afraid
that there's any כתובה, Kesuvah, no כתובה Kesuvah circulating around, there's nothing
to be afraid of. I jumped ahead by saying that in such
a place you would use receipts. Forget that for now. Basically what
we're saying now is one says we do write receipts and the
other says we don't write receipts but there's no כתובה Kesuvah to
be afraid of, no כתובה Kesuvah was written. So the גמרא Gemara
says if no כתובה Kesuvah was written, how could you say no
כתובה Kesuvah was written? It says the כתובה Kesuvah was lost. Clearly
there was a כתובה. Kesuvah. So he wrote it. So but if
he wrote it, we're back to square one. If he wrote it
and there's a כתובה, Kesuvah, let's be afraid that she'll use... Since
you
are saying that since you, who has it, since you are רב
פפא Rav Pappa are saying that we don't
write receipts, so who, so how, so and there happened even if
it's a generally placed that there's no כתובה, Kesubah, but here there
was a כתובה, Kesubah, so why aren't we afraid that she's going
to use it to collect from him again? סוף סוף מפקע לה
וגביה. sof sof mafka lah vegavya. No. מה עיבדא עיבדא בביעור. ma
ivda ivda bebeur. No, it means that we know it was destroyed.
It was like it got burnt up. So therefore there's no afraid
fear that she's going to come and use it again. אי הכי
ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, היינו נשרפה, hainu
nisrefa, we have that as another case. It got burnt. The first
case clearly is we don't know that it got destroyed. ועוד הטמינה
מאי איכא למימר, veod hitmina mai ika lemeimar, it says that she
secreted it, hid it. So clearly we don't know that it's destroyed,
it might be around. So if there's no receipt, why are we,
how can we allow this case? Maybe she's going to extract her
כתובה Kesubah later. So the גמרא Gemara says וכי עיבדא למה לי,
vechi ivda lamma li, and then why would you need the case
of עיבדא? ivda? אלא כל עיבדא כי הטמינה בפנינו דמי. ella kol
ivda ki hitmina bifneinu dami. Okay, fine. Anytime she says it's lost,
here's the way you read the משנה. Mishna. She says it's lost.
Saying it's lost, we suspect that you're hiding it. And therefore you
can't collect, okay? כי הטמינה בפנינו דמי. ki hitmina bifneinu dami. ולא
יהבינן לה, vlo yavhinan lah, we don't give her, עד דאמרי עדים
נשרפה כתובתה, ad deamri eidim nisrefa kesubasa, until the witnesses say it
was burnt. So here's how he reads the משנה, Mishna, the ברייתא.
Baraisa. The ברייתא Baraisa said עיבדא הטמינה נשרפה. ivda hitmina nisrefa. So
it sounded like in all three of those cases she just has
to produce עדים eidim and she's believed. But no, this is how
רב פפא Rav Pappa is reading it. If she says it was
lost, עיבדא, ivda, we say הטמינה, hitmina, we say you're, you're hiding
it and we're afraid you're going to use it somewhere else. And
therefore, we're not going to let you collect. Only if it's נשרפה,
nisrefa, then we'll let you collect. Then we know that it's not
around and you're going to come and use it again. So right
now what we're saying is, the easier read about all of this
is, of course we let her collect and we just tell the
guy hold on to your שובר. shovar. But if you're of the
position I don't like receipts, I reject receipts, if there's nothing to
produce, no שטר shtar to produce, I'm not going to let you
collect, how do you explain these cases? Either there was no כתובה
Kesubah ever so there's nothing to worry about number one, or it's
a place שלא כתבין כתובה, shelo kasvin kesubah, or there was a
כתובה Kesubah but we have absolute evidence that it's been destroyed. Okay,
but if, but if there's ever a possibility that there's a written
כתובה Kesubah around, I'm not going to let you collect without the
כתובה. Kesubah. That's what רב פפא Rav Pappa would say.
And he reads the ברייתא Baraisa as a dialogue. Exactly, he says
עיבדא ivda and they say אהא הטמינה,
aha hitmina, something like that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay, מאן דמתני אברייתא, man demasni ala braisa, where are we,
מאן דמתני אברייתא כל שכן אמתניתין, man demasni ala braisa kolsheken a
matnisitin, and
if you're prepared to reread the ברייתא Baraisa that says it was
lost to say that actually it means that we don't believe her
and that we'll only do it when the כתובה Kesubah is destroyed,
you would certainly say the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna is vague.
ומאן דמתני אמתניתין אבל אברייתא לא כי קשיא. uman demasni a matnisitin
aval abraisa lo ki kashya. But if you just explain that the
משנה Mishna is a case where there is no כתובה, Kesubah, but
about the ברייתא, Baraisa, לא כי קשיא, lo ki kashya, you would
not hold your position by the ברייתא. Baraisa. The ברייתא, Baraisa, the
simple read of the ברייתא Baraisa is much more explicit that even
though there was a כתובה Kesubah you will let her collect, right?
The simple read of the ברייתא Baraisa is not that you have
evidence that the כתובה Kesubah was destroyed. Okay, so basically the משנה
Mishna is vague, the ברייתא Baraisa is pretty clear that even though
you know that there was a כתובה Kesubah and we can't find
it, she's allowed to collect with witnesses. So it really takes a
lot for רב פפא Rav Pappa to say even with that ברייתא
Baraisa I'm going to say that's not true. Once there was a
כתובה Kesubah I will not let her collect, the only time I'm
going to let her collect because I don't believe in receipts and
the only time I'm going to let her collect is if she
can prove either there was never a כתובה Kesubah to begin with
or she can prove that the כתובה Kesubah has been destroyed. Okay,
so that's a big חידוש chiddush to force that into the ברייתא.
Baraisa. But that would be what רב פפא Rav Pappa would say.
Now we're going to get to what I jumped ahead to say,
so let's just read this. ואי איכא עדים, ve-ei ika eidim, if
there are witnesses right that it was a first wedding she can
collect. So the גמרא Gemara says ולימא דילמא מפקא עדי הינומה בהאי
בי דינא וגביא והדר מפקא עדי הינומה בבי דינא אחרינא וגביא. vleima
dilma mafka adei hinuma behaei bei dina vegavya vehadar mafka adei hinuma
bebei dina achrina vegavya.
So finally the גמרא Gemara is getting around to say, so נו,
nu, so even with witnesses let's afraid that she's going to use
witnesses in two different בתי דין. batei din. And even if the
witnesses don't agree there were a lot of wedding guests, so use
one set in one בית דין, beis din, one set in another
בית דין. beis din. So if you have a שובר, shovar, again
if you believe that there is a receipt, you're covered. But if
you're of the position that we never write receipts what do you
do with this? So the גמרא Gemara says no, במקום דלא אפשר
ודאי כתבינן שובר. bemakom dlo efshar vadai kasvinan shovar. If there's no
alternative you certainly write a שובר, shovar, which means this is what
I had jumped ahead to before. If there's no כתובה Kesubah around,
okay, and you're going to go, if the place שלא כתבין כתובה,
shelo kasvin kesubah, there is no כתובה Kesubah to begin with, okay,
so in that type of a scenario where there's no כתובה Kesubah
to begin with, of course you're going to do a שובר. shovar.
What alternative do you have? You don't want the person to go
ahead and to be able to collect twice, maybe if there's a
concern that there's different types of עדים eidim that you could use
one set and one and one set in the other. So you
have no choice you'll write a שובר. shovar. But when you started
with a כתובה, Kesubah, then we're not going to have any רחמנות.
rachmanus. If we start with a document, you've got to hold on
to that document. And if you've lost it that's your tough luck
and the only thing that we'll consider is maybe if the document
was like destroyed in front of our eyes. But other than that
it's your tough luck, we will refuse to write a, we will
refuse to write a receipt. That's when you start with a document.
But when you didn't start with a document or when let's say
the document was destroyed in front of us so we know there's
no document around, then there's no alternative, then we will write a
שובר Shover at least to protect from collecting twice even without a
document.
Yeah, שובר Shover is only written in the case where they don't
write a כתובה. Kesuvah. According to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, yes. Where
they write a כתובה Kesuvah she'd have to hand it over.
And without the document exactly and without the document you're stuck. That's
רב פפא, Rav Pappa, okay? רב פפא Rav Pappa completely rejects the
idea of שוברים. Shoverim. He has to allow for it in some
cases where there's nothing to be done, okay, but basically if you
started with a document and if you can't prove it was destroyed,
we will refuse to write a כתובה. Kesuvah.
Now like they did if the כתובה Kesuvah was paid out they
cut it or they...
Yeah. Yeah. So now let's just do a little bit here, we'll
end today's דף Daf with some of the practices that show that
it was a first wedding. This will be fun. Nice softer ending
to the דף Daf or whatever. מביאים לפניה כוס של בשורה, Mevi'in
lefaneha kos shel besora, the goblet of well-wishes. מאי כוס של בשורה?
Mai kos shel besora? אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, Amar Rav Adda
bar Ahava, כוס יין של תרומה מביאים לפניה, Kos yayin shel Terumah
mevi'in lefaneha, a cup filled with תרומה Terumah wine. כלומר ראויה הייתה
זו לאכול בתרומה, Kelomar reu'ya hayta zu le'echol bi'Terumah, she's a בתולה,
Besulah, she's never had sex before, so we don't have to worry
about the fact that if she's marrying a כהן, Kohen, of course
who says it was a כהן's Kohen's wedding? But anyway we don't
have to be worrying about the fact that she
might have had sex with a man that would have made her
פסול Pasul to the כהן. Kohen. So notice again by the way
the cup filled with wine, again the very red liquid, blood, all
this imagery, okay fine. Anyway, it's all about her being a בתולה.
Besulah. So anyway מתקיף לה רב פפא, Matkif lah Rav Pappa, so
רב פפא Rav Pappa asks אטו אלמנה מי לא אכלה בתרומה? Atu
almana mi lo achla bi'Terumah? I don't get it, just because a
woman it's not a first wedding doesn't mean that she can't and
she's marrying a כהן Kohen doesn't mean
she can't eat תרומה. Terumah. She could be an אלמנה. Almana. That's
not about her being a בתולה. Besulah. It's not like a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol she has to be a בתולה. Besulah. So anyway
so אלא אמר רב פפא, Ella amar Rav Pappa, זו ראשית כתרומה.
Zu reishit ke'Terumah. No, here was the symbolism. תרומה Terumah is first.
ראשית עריסותיכם, Reishit arisoteichem, you know, ראשית תרימו תרומה, Reishit tarimu Terumah,
it's the first thing that you separate off. So this is תרומה
Terumah fine whatever. This is תרומה, Terumah, this is the first, and
this is going to be the first time that she's going to
have sex. All right, so זו ראשית כתרומה, Zu reishit ke'Terumah, זו
ראשית כתרומה ראשית. Zu reishit ke'Terumah reishit. Okay, like תרומה Terumah's a
ראשית. Reishit. תניא רבי יהודה אומר, Tanya Rabi Yehuda omer, חבית של
יין מביאים לפניה, Chavis shel yayin mevi'in lefaneha, a barrel of wine.
Remember before we had the barrel of wine with the rag that
was they first of all they sat on the barrel of wine
and then the rag in the hole that you were squeezing in
the holes and the whatever, okay fine, it's all connected. So אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה, Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, in case you
missed the significance, says רב אדא בר אהבה, Rav Adda bar Ahava,
בתולה מביאים לפניה סתומה, Besulah mevi'in lefaneha setumah, a בתולה Besulah you
carry a closed cask of wine. בעולה מביאים לפניה פתוחה, Be'ulah mevi'in
lefaneha petucha, a בעולה Be'ulah מביאים לפניה פתוחה. mevi'in lefaneha petucha.
Oh my god. Let's assume it means a second wedding I guess,
not that
you're announcing to everybody whether she's had sex before. Anyway, but if
it's a second wedding it's an open barrel of wine. Oh my
god, אמאי Amai says the גמרא? Gemara? ניעבר קמיה בתולה? Na'aver kamei
besulah? Why don't we just have the barrel of wine for the
בתולה? Besulah? וקמיה בעולה לא ניעבר כלל, U'kamei be'ulah lo na'aver kelal,
and not have anything for a בעולה? Be'ulah? No, זימנין דתפסה מאתיים,
Zimnin di'tafsa masayim, maybe sometimes she'll
seize her husband's property, so it'll be the המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה
Ha'motzi mei'chaveiro alav ha'reayah on him. He'll have taken possession of the
property so she'll have the presumption, you know, he'll have to prove
that it wasn't a first wedding because she's now holding on to
the money.
ואמרה, Ve'amrah, and she'll say בתולה הוינא, Besulah havina, you know what,
even though you can bring witnesses that said there was no barrel
of wine, it doesn't matter, I was a first wedding. והאי דלא
עברו קמאי, Ve'hai di'lo avru kamai, why didn't they have the barrel
of wine? איטנוסי הוא דאיטנוסו, Itnusi hu di'itnusu, they were so drunk
or whatever they never got around to it. So therefore we don't
want to have the absence of evidence, we want actually there to
be concrete evidence either way. So if they have the open barrel
closed barrel it's concrete evidence she was a בתולה Besulah and an
open barrel it's concrete evidence that she was not. Because if we
just have the lack of the wine she could always explain why
they never got around to doing the whole wine the whole fun
wine practice. Okay, so we are getting a nice interesting insight into
some of the wedding
practices and we will continue with this.
So you're getting back to me these days, you know, this is
interesting question so like let's say she said you know what you
know we were together on the wedding night you weren't a virgin
she says.